Welcome Mental Health Monday family.
It's so good to have you all here with
us this evening. Please let us know
where you are viewing from. We want to
say a special welcome to all of you and
we want to see where you are viewing
from as we are continuing our
conversation this evening about men's
mental health. Such a big topic. I know
when I announced it um uh this past week
at church, I said, "Please, women, come.
You are welcome because you need to know
how to take care of the men in your life
or at least how to check in on the men
in your life to see that they're okay.
Um because it's so very important." And
of course, they need to do the same for
you. But today we are talking about
men's uh mental health and some of the
special challenges that that men go
through and women. We know you have
special challenges too and when we do it
the topic is on women. We'll definitely
be covering those as well. But again
today is on men. Welcome Clint. You
definitely were the first one. I don't
know if you were the first one here. If
you were the first one I know you're the
first one to write in the chat. So
welcome. Clint is like all over the
place. Clint was on last night when we
did um the part two of the T horns. Uh
Clint was there. Clint's at Clint is
everywhere. Clint is
>> representing.
>> He's good people.
>> That's awesome. [laughter]
>> Clint, we appreciate you. We appreciate.
>> Yes, we have Tra. I don't Travis. I
don't know if that's the last name, but
from Florida. We have a device. I've
learned to say it's device. You don't
know how many people are watching,
right? So we say we have somebody is
watching from Florida on a device
[laughter]
because we don't know. We we don't know.
I really Yeah, I've heard
desktop or mobile. True.
>> Yeah, because you never know if it's one
person. Rebecca, welcome. Rebecca, where
are you where are you viewing from?
>> Like to just know where all of our
audience is is coming from. But we're
just happy uh that you guys are here
with us. Um,
Clint says, "The Lord is keeping him
busy." We're just thankful that you are
here with us.
>> With us. I don't think I said hi to you,
Dr. White. Hi.
>> Greetings, Sister Tante. How are you?
>> Yes, I I'm doing well. I told you when I
was like rushing to the the home studio
that I was like, I was just into seeing
a client like 15 20 minutes ago. So, I'm
okay. But, I'm like, it's been a busy
day. It's been a busy Monday. Definitely
busy Monday.
>> Rebecca is watching from viewing from
South Dakota. Wow. Welcome. I have never
been to the Dakotas. Have you, Dr.
White?
>> I
said that quickly, but I don't believe
so. I've been to Minnesota or maybe even
Min Minneapolis, but no, I haven't.
>> That's Minnesota. Yeah, but the Dakotas
are Yeah. South Dakota. Dakota, North
Dakota. Rebecca, how cold is it there?
Do you guys have a lot of snow? I always
just imagine the Dakotas have a lot of
snow even in the summer. I know they
don't have all that snow in the summer,
but you just think Dakotas, you just
think snow, beautiful white snow. But
>> yeah, let us know. Emily, welcome. Don't
know where you're viewing from, but it's
good to have you here with us today as
we talk about men's mental health. Yes.
>> So, we were able to take um we at least
a good introduction into men's mental
health last week. Um, I think it was it
was so good that we decided to make this
a series. Um, because it I think I know
men deserve that much attention.
>> Oh, thank you for saying that. You know,
there's there there people who don't
even wouldn't even agree, you know, like
sometimes it just feels so you just feel
overlooked. And and what and what's
funny is
I think a lot of times we kind of don't
want to be in the limelight like that,
you know,
>> and so it's like we we almost kind of
embrace being like, "Yeah, we don't have
to talk about that. It's I'm
uncomfortable." Like, "Yeah, let's No,
let's talk about you guys, you know."
>> Yeah.
>> So So it's it's very awesome that you
would resonate with it and be like, "No,
this is important." So thank you.
>> Yes. Well, we have to give sister
Denise. It was her idea, then you
resonated with it, and then I resonated
with it. So, we're all three resonating
with [laughter] the fact that we need to
talk about men's mental health.
>> Um, it is but it is a huge huge huge um
topic, I have to say. Um, I mean, things
are changing in the world though.
They're definitely changing. I don't
know about you, but um I see
I see I mean I I'm starting to see more
and more men reach out for therapy.
>> Oh yeah,
>> that's a shift. That's definitely a
shift and change in soci in society for
sure.
>> Agreed. Agreed. Agreed. I mean, I I have
a good chunk of men that, you know, we
we
that we see from an acute, you know,
locked in psychiatric perspective.
Unfortunately,
like that part of the population,
they're being brought into the hospital
in some situations
even against their wills. So,
>> yeah,
>> like they're not like voluntarily
coming. it's because of anger issues and
being explosive and and so I would
highly recommend you get the support you
need before it comes to that. So
>> So you're you're right though. It is
nice that there is a movement towards
>> come before you have to go see Dr.
White. [laughter]
>> I didn't want to say it that way, but
>> Well, that's right. That's really what
it is.
>> That's but that's that's
>> come to me voluntarily before they force
you to see Dr. [laughter] White.
before the law says, "You know what? You
we're gonna put you on a three-day hold
and [laughter]
>> or the family, you know, scoop you up
into the car before that." No,
>> she's going to be a much better day.
[laughter]
>> Yes.
>> The day you see me on.
>> Most definitely. Listen, you guys are
definitely a part of this program. We
are going to be sharing uh things that
uh we have learned and want to share
with you about uh men's mental health
and how to improve that and giving some
tips and those things like of that
nature. But we want to hear your
questions. We want to you are a part of
it by asking us questions so we can um
you know be able to answer those
questions. And I'm happy to see some
women here. The women that are are here,
welcome. We're so happy to see you here
because again um you are going to be
learning some things on how to be able
to better support the men in your life.
So
>> when we don't see questions, we will ask
because I do have a question for you.
>> You have a question for me?
>> I got a question.
>> All right, let's go. Dr. Wright always
does this. He always has questions for
me way before I have questions for him.
But go ahead.
>> What What has a man surprised you and
asked you in therapy? What were you what
were what kind of shocked you that that
you were actually asked about in therapy
or the situation you had to deal with
that kind of stands out to you
>> that surprised me
that a man asked? Um,
it didn't. Well, I don't know how much I
guess I could say it was a surprise
because I was just learning. I've just
never had a man say this before, but I
had a man years ago. Um, he said, and it
was in couples counseling. So, he just
explained to me and it helped me to
understand
what it's like as a man when a woman or
your wife or your your partner is um
asking you a ton of questions and you're
and and the man is not answering fast
enough. and how frustrating and how
difficult that is. I he enlightened me
cuz I didn't and I didn't realize that
the way we process or the way women
process information so quickly. A man is
just like they're processing it way
slower than we're than we are. I mean, I
see it in our my marriage all the time.
I'll just be honest. like I need to let
my husband sit with something and give
him some time to like I'm like so what's
your answer? What do you think? Well,
give me an answer. And he's like
processing it at his speed and it seems
like they're just shutting down, but
they're not. They're processing and we
don't give them enough time to process.
I had to learn that. My client literally
is teaching me something. He didn't know
that though, but he was teaching me. I
think that's so profound because
>> when he he did he painted the picture so
>> using his words I could see it. It just
like and it penetrated so hard with me
because I was like wow I do that
sometimes. I can see it. I see I can see
I shut down sometimes because I'm just
like give me an answer. What do you
mean? Hurry. You know I'm like it's like
this but for a man it's like your guys'
processing will goes like probably
slower than that and ours is like this.
But go ahead. Well, well, well, the
funny thing is like so like if you're if
you're like analyzing it and you're
about to get to a conclusion, then it's
like, well, what do you think? And so
now you got to restart it again.
[laughter]
>> Exactly.
>> And then you're like re So no, but I
need you. What do you think? And it's
like, so that's where the shutdown
happens because you're just like, I'm
trying to get to the conclusion, you
know? I'm taking it through my system.
So that that's really that that's really
refreshing. And for women, what I
learned and I, you know, was something
that I think that a lot of you as women
could learn and take away is be patient.
Let and it could not even be your your
husband or partner, even with your son
or father or brother or co-orker or
whatever. These are men. So, give them
time to process and get the answer out.
>> That's wild.
>> Be patient.
>> That's wild. That's hard for us.
>> I I do want to I do want to compliment
you and how you work with pastor
>> because like like
you like he's going he's deep diving
into the 10 horns or the whatever it is.
But it's like
>> so
>> but but then it's like you'll be like
okay well don't forget this the
schedule. Okay, go deeper on this point
or all right, but remember there's some
people like it's like
>> it it just it's this perfect marriage,
you know,
>> um by the grace of God, you know,
>> I do think we compliment each other
well.
>> We have learned a lot. We grow God put
us together so we could both grow and
learn and be better people because we
had to like, you know, his strengths are
my weaknesses and my strengths are his
weaknesses. So, we like we compliment
each other. But um yeah, I
>> But that's a dance that it's nice to try
to learn
>> with your spouse because it's
>> Yeah, we had to learn to how to dance
together. [laughter]
>> It's you have to learn it, you know, and
it's so I mean I think that's what
>> um now Clint just gave my book a shout
out. Clint, I appreciate you, brother. I
>> did. He picked up my Killing Burnout
book and he said he's enjoying it.
>> I appreciate that, Clint. Thank you so
much for that.
>> Yes. He said, "It's been a huge
blessing." I saw that. A huge All right.
Yes.
>> Awesome. Thank you.
>> It is a great book. I've told you I've
I've used your material. I've given
talks using your material. I did give
you credit though. I told them the book.
[laughter]
>> I appreciate that. I appreciate that.
>> I let them know this this didn't come
from me. This is where it came from. But
yes, no, it's a great book. So guys,
Killing Burnout, you want to check that
out. But it looks like we have a
question. Do you believe if a if a man
chose to stay single is unhealthy?
>> Good question.
>> Uber. I don't Well, we don't know. But
Uber, great question. Great question.
>> It is a great question. I'm going to
process that slowly like I was saying
that how men do.
>> I'm letting you answer first and then
I'm going to process if I'm going to
come up with an answer.
>> Sure. Um so it can be healthy and it can
be unhealthy. Um so the the deciding
factor then becomes
why
and what will they do you know in
instead. So what when can it be healthy?
It could be it could be super healthy if
a person is like hey man I'm really
committed to a vision. I'm committed to
a dream of some sort and I recognize
that it would be unfair to bring a you
know to start a relationship with the
with the expectations.
Um so I know when I was you know when I
was dating and I w and I was on a
medical track my wife understood okay I
know what that requires. um she was a
nurse so she was pretty familiar but so
I know what that requires and there are
other people who they'd be like I don't
want to be with a doctor I don't I don't
want to deal with that level of demand
and
>> and so so it might have been wise for me
to say okay well I'll be single until
maybe a certain point [clears throat]
>> where I have greater command of my
schedule now it can so you can see how
you can make a decision where it could
be healthy but it could be unhealthy If,
for example, a person just wanted to be
self-centered
>> and just make life about themsel and
hey, I'm just going to focus on me.
Well, what you find is
often when you're going to get fantastic
outcomes,
it you you you're able to attach to a
vision that's bigger than yourself.
>> When you get a vision that's bigger than
yourself, a lot of times you get better
outcomes. And the other interesting
thing to that is when you when you get
into a relationship, it can often be a
source where it brings more out of you.
You're like, "Okay, now I'm not just
living for me. I'm living for this other
person." And you know, you know, when
you had kids, oh my goodness, when you
have kids, it can be so centering and
like, okay, it's one thing if I was just
relying on this, but my family is
depending on this. It's a different
pull. So, so I think if it's just kind
of just self-centerness, then it can
sometimes be unhealthy. Now, that's what
came to my mind. But since now that
you've had some time to reflect on it,
what are your thoughts?
>> I I 100% agree with you. Um
if I want to go um
I agree with you and if I want to go
Bible, you know, the Bible says it's not
healthy for man to be alone. Um I I I I
truly think that. Now there are there
Jesus was not married. He was alone. He
did have a mission. So I uh Paul
um once converted was alone and um and
was very focused on the ministry that he
was called to. So using those examples,
there are examples but they're few
examples um like that meaning that could
be
the calling for for some um
and you know that that's what would be
best. But I can say that um overall the
majority of of course what you said
especially bringing children in and I
have to say
I'm not a man I'm a woman but being with
someone being with my husband has made
me a better person.
>> Being a mother I can tell you the three
things have made me a well I guess I
could say four. I mean I had great
parenting. I have to say that. But that
what's really made me a better person is
my husband becoming a mother becoming a
therapist. those three things.
>> That's a good point. That's a really
That's a good point because sometimes
I'm using skills and I'm just like, man,
these are things I've learned. Imagine
imagine how this situation would have
unfolded if I didn't have this training.
I didn't learn and and I was going to
[clears throat] say um that you know
especially
you're going to be very it's very easy
to be self-centered if you're not in a
rel in a committed marital relationship
or even as a parent because all you have
to do is worry about yourself.
So, it it's it can be challenging to
um have to learn to have empathy
um when you're not in that situation. Is
is that is it impossible? No. Do we know
for everybody's situation? We're not God
and we don't know his will for every
single person. But
>> overall, I know that um I I'll just be
honest like who who knows people that
have never been married or never had
children? I know some people like that.
And um yeah, that's all. They're just if
you've never had to give your life to
little people that grow up to be, you
know, great, you know, adults or to give
your life or to when I say give your
life like sacrifice
[clears throat and cough] yourself and
things you want to do. It's almost like
you know being you know like even with
only children they have to learn how to
share like with cousins or friends or
you know learn those because they don't
learn that at home because they don't
have to automatically share anything.
I'm seeing this I'll just give you guys
an example. Um, I mean it's not about
sharing, but it's just about how because
we have three grandchildren and the
middle grandson now was only 18 months
when this baby was born a month ago. And
his mind was blown. He was his mother's
whole world even though I we had an
older granddaughter who was who was
almost five. This was our daughter's
first son, the middle one. And so when
this next baby this when the baby came a
month ago, he's like, "Mom, it was me
and you. I was I was your guy. Now
you're spending all this time with this
little baby. My point is is he's
learning how to share.
>> How to share.
>> He's learning that yes, mommy loves him
and daddy loves him, but their whole
world doesn't just revolve around him.
My granddaughter had to learn that. I'm
just giving I'm going way into the only
children thing. But just like we only
children are having children, the
children learn when the other children
come into the picture. We also learn
when we have children as parents um how
what it's like to just be
self-sacrificing
um to these little children that you
created and brought into the world. So
>> we we could we could keep batting this
question around because like
>> being married has helped me and it's
it's ways where it's so intangible like
>> there are there are wardrobe
catastrophes that my wife has helped me
to avoid, you know, like And to a degree
vice versa, it's as little as, hey, does
this work? And it's like, that does not
work.
>> My husband always asks me, he's like,
what do you think about this? And then
when he doesn't, and then like just the
other day, I was like, why do you have
that on? [laughter]
>> Right. Well,
>> he's like, well, I thought the other
thing was too much. I was like, no, that
was better. This is not enough. Or, you
know, Yeah, I agree.
>> We help one another. We help one
another.
>> We help one another. We help one another
100%. So,
>> so you can tell we're pretty much team
marriage when you marry the right person
and you know and it's but but again
it's something that you have to to make
that decision. So, I think we took a
long time on that one. Let's go to
another question. Why do men tend to
share their emotions with other men,
example, their male friends, more than
they do with women, including their
wives? I'm letting you answer this first
because I think you know better than I
do
>> why y'all do this.
>> So, here I'll give you a I'll give you a
um I'll give you an illustration. I
remember being part of a men's Bible
study. And by the way, that's one of the
things that helped me be a better person
as well. So, shout out to Mount Rubo
men's Bible study. Um it it was
definitely one of the things that helped
me grow in many directions. Well, I want
to give a shout out to the Living Mana
uh Church men's group because we have a
men's ministry. A lot of them are here
today, so I think we have to give a
shout out to them, too. Maybe you need
to to visit the men's group for Living
Man Church as well. But go ahead.
>> Well, brothers, brothers, put a one in
the chat if I was on a call with you
just last week.
>> Okay. And they are know because I'm not
a part of the [laughter]
No, they are epic. They are epic. So,
I'm looking forward to Yeah, I'm
definitely looking forward to get It's
dude, it's a hidden gem. So, absolute
shout out to Living Mana um men's group.
>> I think every man should be in a men's
group somewhere.
>> No qu. Well, and every living mana man
should be in our Living Mana um
>> Well, for sure. Absolutely. Absolutely.
>> It's at 5 I think it's 5:30 p.m. Central
Standard Time on Tuesdays if I'm not
mistaken. I don't. So, you guys might
put something in the chat to um clarify,
but it can be you're it can be so
helpful to be in community with
likeminded brethren. [clears throat]
Now, we're getting to your point. Now,
we're getting to your question here,
Deborah.
One of the things I think men tend to
understand
is like if your brother is dealing with
emotions I think we have a tremendous
amount of respect for it. So in that
men's Bible study from time to time a
person might be crying but I think men
understand that behind those tears like
by the time a man is brought to the
point of crying
>> it's a really significant moment. You
see this big built dude crying. You
understand that person is at the edge.
And so we we will tend to by default
handle that with tremendous care.
>> And I think sometimes outside of the
setting of men that can it can it can be
mishandled.
It can be mishandled.
>> Um whether it's a joke might be made,
whether it might be dismissed in some
way. Um,
so that it's like, hey, I want to I want
to I want to do this in the space where
for whatever reason I'm deeming this as
a safe space. Like that's the thing that
comes to mind. That's the thing that
comes to mind, Deborah. Um, but there
can be other things as well. Um, and so,
so if they've had a bad experience where
maybe they they they did it to a woman
and then she responded in a way that
hurt them subsequently or it was
weaponized against them subsequently, it
could lead them to say, "I feel safer
doing this with some men that I've built
some trust and community with versus
taking it out of this setting." What are
your thoughts, sis?
>> I I absolutely 100% agree with you, and
I would say it like this. I think I can
say it because I'm a woman. Um,
sometimes ladies, I mean,
we're okay, I'm saying this, we can be
we sometimes it can be our fault that
they feel safer to talk in their um
around their male friends or in with
just men because their walls might be up
because they've tried to
um talk to us or a woman in their, you
know, in their in their life. and um
she shut them down or didn't listen,
became
um you know frustrated and angry and
just they just didn't feel safe.
>> Yeah, I concur.
>> And so they and so and so this is and I
can say
I don't know this is not a scientific
proven tested theory. This is my theory,
[laughter]
but I feel like when men get shut down,
they're ve men are men are strong. They
are the protectors and all of that. Like
if somebody's about to approach you or
hurt you, like something just clicks and
they're like, "No, I'm the man here. I'm
going to fight for this my wife, child,
or that I'm protecting them." But
emotionally when they get shut down by
women,
um it can be very difficult for them to
get the courage to put themselves in
that position again to just be shut down
or hurt again. You can tell me if I'm
very off,
>> Dr. White. Um so they don't really allow
themsel I'll give you an example. Okay,
we're just gonna we're talking real talk
right here. Okay, guys. Um, we know that
men and women cheat, right? They can be
unfaithful in their in their marriage.
But I have learned at a early age, I saw
this. This is like high school. So, you
know, in high school, people are not
mature and they're doing things they
should not be doing. But when a guy
really really really really liked a girl
and if and this is like let's just say
high school and she cheated
he was so wounded he never got over that
maybe years later it turned him into
like a mass cheater. He never trusted
again. He was too scared to be that good
faithful man again because he doesn't
want to get hurt. So they kind of it
kind of turns them into a a chronic
cheater until they finally get healed
and get themselves together and later on
in life hopefully they get out of that.
But I've seen that happen many times and
it just made me think like men once they
put their heart out there and you heard
it it is very hard for them to trust
again. And I'm not saying women don't go
through a lot of deep pain if they got
che when they get cheated on as well.
But I have found that women seem to be a
little bit more resilient
and they will be faithful in that next
situation even though they were hurt in
the last situation.
>> I'm not saying for every single
situation. I've just seen that many
times. Again, this is not a scientific
study. It's my experience of what I've
seen. What?
>> You're cooking with Crisco. Um
>> Crisco a good oil. Say I'm cooking with
olive oil. Crisco is not a healthy oil,
but go ahead.
>> You're cooking with extra virgin olive
oil. Okay. extra virgin.
>> You know who would appreciate that is um
Columbus Dr. Batist. [laughter]
>> Columbus Batist. Yeah.
>> I'll be like, do can you believe that
Ricardo told me I'm cooking with Crisco?
He would [laughter]
>> You're cooking with extra virgin hol
olive oil with the high temperature set
point.
>> Organic extra virgin
>> organic whole.
>> Yeah. Um well because I don't know now
we're going into the um the cheating
thing but it's like when on a whole when
you look at why women cheat when you
look at why men cheat
>> um so a lot of times when women cheat
there's emotions involved like it's it's
it's more of an emotion
>> um and then you look at men cheat um and
it's it can often be a bit more like
physical obviously you can't really just
separate physical from emotions
obviously there's some emotion involved
But like you can you you can imagine how
a women's group of friends look at her
if she's being cheated on and think
about how a group of men look at that
person who's being cheated on and you
can immediately see [snorts] like as
guys you're looking at the person like
you know it it's you know you so so as a
woman you are defending that guy's
self-respect
Right?
>> Like you're literally defending it
>> as a as a guy. You're defending her
self-respect. It's true. But if you got
that analogy just now, you got it. If
you didn't get it, sorry. But but yeah,
so whatever the case, um making that
setting safe for that man is critical.
And it may very well start with just
having the conversation. You know, what
would make it safe? What what would make
me easy to talk to? Um here and here's
how you might ask the question. What's
one thing I could do to make it easier
to talk to me?
>> What's one thing? Just what what's one
thing I could do?
>> Write that down, ladies. Write that
down.
>> What's one thing I could do to make it a
little easier to talk to me? Just one.
>> Absolutely. [clears throat and cough]
>> Absolutely.
How can I help? How can I better make
you feel safe? That's beautiful. That's
beautiful. Have another question. How
can I keep um from um I guess getting
stressed out and social situations when
I'm introverted and have some level of
social anxiety? That is from David.
>> Um that's a that's a powerful question.
Um so here's the thing. Social anxiety
it'll it'll occur on a spectrum. And so
there's a spectrum where just a talk
recommendation might be helpful to you
and you do these tweaks and it might
work. But it's on the other spectrum
where hey I wonder if professional
attention is necessary and psych
psychopharmarmacological intervention is
required like meds are so it's a
spectrum but so all we're locked into is
you know we're going to deal with the
making recommendations so that's maybe
on the lighter end of the spectrum. I
know for me, David,
it helped me to navigate social settings
um with greater ease when I was able to
take my focus out of my emotions
and
understand, you know, there's probably
somebody here who's just as
uncomfortable as I feel right now. And
if if I can make it a point to kind of
focus on them and try to make them
comfortable,
um it'll distract me from how I'm
feeling.
>> And and I mean the the powerful thing is
when like you really approach it that
way and like you even ratchet it up. You
know, there's somebody here who is maybe
at their wits end. like what if I was
able to be present for that person?
There's a there's a person that might be
hopeless. They might be desperate. Um
they might be tempted to give up because
no one has talk to them meaningfully.
What if I found that person? What if
what if I was present for conversation
and and really gave a person a chance to
talk about something they cared about?
We've all had those cocktail parties
where you got an opportunity to talk
about something you cared about,
>> right?
>> That's the fun
>> and the person listened and they were
present.
>> David, what I'm talking about is
shifting the focus from my heart rate is
going up and what are people thinking
about how I'm dressed and what are they
thinking and what to
>> to let me focus on making sure this
person feels heard. M
>> they'd feel heard and I go up to the
first person and it went flat. Maybe
they ignored me. Worst case scenario, I
just went to the next person. Well, I
guess that wasn't the mission. But that
that's what you could be seeking for.
And let's say the night goes horribly,
David. At the end of the night, you can
say to yourself, I was ready to be
present for someone. I did it.
>> I did it. That's awesome.
>> What are your thoughts?
>> Yes. No, I Yeah. No, I love your um
again I agree with you. I think that's
great information. I'll just add a
little caveat to that uh because you
mentioned like you know when you're
having anxiety your heart is beating
faster. Um and so I mean and this is for
women or this is for us humans period.
It doesn't matter men or women but um
when I am feeling anxiety and this is
what I teach my uh clients a lot and
I've talked about this on here before
but just do the the deep breathing the
four seven nine taking a deep breath and
people don't even know it was perfect
during co when we had to wear mask it
was absolutely perfect because nobody
knew nothing but they could still not
know anything like even before I go on
live like on um Sabbath mornings I do I
do my deep breathing before I go live
before I'm like Hello, welcome. I mean,
it's just to calm me down and just to
completely shut down any
anxiety or anything. And so, you are
lowering your heart rate, calming down,
and then you can have that conversation
in your head that you did that Dr. White
just talked about. So, you're bringing
yourself back into the center and be
like, you know what? Then you can
capture those negative thoughts that are
like, oh, they're looking at what you're
wearing or they're looking at or they're
listening to every word you're saying if
you're saying it right. like all those
negative things that go on in our head
when we're in social situations. So the
breathing, take a deep breath for four
counts, hold it for seven, release it
for nine, bring the heart rate down, do
as many times as needed.
>> One more time with that count. One more
time with that count. Can you give that
count one more time?
>> 479.
>> 479. In 4 seconds,
>> hold it for seven.
>> Yeah.
>> Let it out for nine.
>> Let it out for nine. Like you're let
like like you're deflating a balloon.
letting all the air out of your lungs
and breathe again. [laughter]
>> Very cool. How many cycles would you
say?
>> You know, I always tell my clients
three. Um, but honestly, the first time
immediately your heart rate is going to
start to come down, but then, you know,
sometimes anxiety is so much like three
is golden. Um, but maybe you only have
an opportunity for one that will still
help, but three is like a nice spot.
>> 100%.
Yes, Greg agree. You said a ton.
Controlling the vag nerve. Absolutely.
Um that's a whole another that's a whole
another thing, but we'll talk about that
next time. There's different ways to to
activate the vagus nerve. Okay. I have
found it hardest to learn to listen to
my own personal cues with internal
struggles because I used to ignore them.
I certainly do better now. But do you
have advice concerning this? This is
from our from Clint.
>> Yeah. Um so Clint, this is where the
morning devotion hour is so critical. Um
because that morning time
is where you do have an opportunity to
attune to God but you also have an
opportunity to attune to your own
thoughts.
>> And you know this is like so this is why
meditative periods can be example. This
is why the the journaling can be
important because it's these are moments
to externalize your thoughts to where
you then can interrogate them. you can
see what you're thinking and and then
with with it externalized with it out
there with it on paper it's easier for
you to say oh that's what I was thinking
now you can process it and now you can
make you know adjustments and I think
that's what attunes you now to your own
personal cues including internal
struggles because you're like man I
didn't even know I was really feeling
that way but right it's right there on
paper as opposed to just an amorphous
internal thought that can come and go
and it's it's it can go without you even
realizing it.
>> Yeah, great question.
>> Absolutely great question.
>> I see the book on Amazon and I will
order. Is it available in audio? Great
question, Uber. Not at this time. I
didn't do audio. I even did iBooks so
that like you get it you can get a
digital copy on um on Apple and we also
did it on
Kind Kindle. Kindle
>> Kindle.
>> I kept wanting to say Kinder like
[laughter]
No, no, no. It's I like that's not
right. That's not I kept rejecting it.
>> Kindle Kindle.
>> Yes.
>> Yes. So they can get the book um on
Amazon. That's great. Um,
>> all right.
>> If a married man wants to see a
therapist, should they talk with a male
therapist?
>> You absolutely can talk to a male
therapist. Um, but I can tell you, um,
female therapists can be great, too. I
mean, it, you know, it's whatever
therapist fits for you, whether it's a
male or a female. Um there's a lot of
different um characteristics of the
therapist that are going to um be able
to for able to create that um therapy
therapist and client alliance which is
so very important. So it could be male,
it could be female.
>> Well said because the goal in therapy
they talk about is the therapeutic
alliance. Like that's like they don't
even talk about the approach, you know?
It's the therapeutic alliance,
>> right?
>> Um yeah, there's a therapeutic alliance
and and get ready for this, too. Like
the first person you try, it's probably
not even going to be the act the the
fit. It's like you often have to do more
than one therapist to land on the
therapist
>> where you get that therapeutic alliance,
right, that will foster the growth that
needs to take place. So
>> absolutely
>> if if you think you need it, try it. Um
but you you might get a a fantastic
outcome working with with a with a
female therapist. You
>> I always tell people don't give up so
easy. Like people some people say, "Oh,
I went to a therapist once and a couple
of times I went and I'm like, "No, no,
no, no. If that one didn't work, you
have to try and try again until you find
the one that you fits with you."
>> That's like saying, um, I dated a
person, it didn't work. So, no marriage
for me.
>> No more dating. [laughter]
>> No more dating.
>> Yeah. No,
>> definitely don't want to do that.
>> Yeah.
>> So, we're still taking your guys's
questions. We have about 10 more minutes
to uh take your questions. So, please uh
throw your questions in there. We're
talking about men's mental health. And
you know, Dr. white. We still um had
quite a list of things from um our last
last week that we we didn't get to.
>> Yeah. Let me see. Men.
>> Yeah. And so we did we we spoke about uh
some of them. We talked about just to
recap a little bit the higher suicide
rates that men that men are um the
there's more suicide rates that are done
completed I should say by men. women
definitely attempt but men tend to make
sure that it it happens. Um
and then depression symptoms for men um
may men may experience depression
differently than women often expressing
it through irritability, anger or
substance abuse rather than just
sadness.
And and that's important because here
you might be preparing to say, "Hey, let
me offer support, right?" And so you're
looking for depressive symptoms when in
fact this person is coming at you with
like aggression, you know?
>> And so aggression you more want to
respond to with aggression.
>> Uh when in and and it could be that, you
know, it's it's actually misunderstood.
um depression. Now, please do not take
that statement to license being
aggressive in your social sphere and
say, "No, I'm just depressed." Please
don't do that. Don't do that. Um I think
as men, a awesome
responsibility we have is to protect um
the environments we're entrusted with
and to as best as possible make people
feel safe wherever, you know, that's
possible. Obviously, you can't be absurd
about these things, but
>> but no, I I wouldn't want to to use the
excuse that, hey, I'm depressed to let
that excuse my aggression. Um, you don't
want to be a bully. I I just think like,
you know, growing up, one of the worst
things a person could be is a bully.
Don't be a bully. Do not misplace your
anger, your frustration on on a
non-deserving target or on any target
honestly.
>> Um, this is why it's you are you are not
responsible for the trauma, but you're
responsible for the healing. That's your
responsibility.
>> That's your respons. It's you can't just
say, well, I've had this traumatic. Not
responsible that it occurred, but you
are responsible for for for the healing.
So, no, you can't just take it out on
the people in your community. Handle it,
you know, get it handled. And that's why
you want to get your support. But in in
the in the things that we in our mutual
list that we have,
>> men struggle with accepting help.
>> They struggle with accepting help. And
>> one needs to overcome that
>> or even asking. We have a question. How
long should a man exercise weight
training slashcardio?
Um I [laughter]
>> Yeah, I guess it it'd be nice if she
like what does what does long mean?
Meaning how long in a workout session?
How long in terms of their life? Um so
that's this is where we have to impose
meaning. So like how long let's so so 30
minutes of cardio is often recommended
but presuming presuming that's safe for
that person as determined by them and
their health you know health
professional. Um but yeah you often hear
um 30 minutes is helpful. Please do not
sleep on the power of walking. Please do
not sleep on on the power of of walk
>> for mental for for physical health and
mental health
>> and mental health.
>> I went to a workshop with two you may
know them because but I don't remember
their names because um I met them
through Dr. Batist so you may know them
but they are a husband and a wife that
are both neurologist.
>> Okay. Well, think about it. They they
did mention that the best thing to do
for to to help prevent dementia later in
life is walking. We should be walking.
We should you start walking like in your
30s 40 I mean earlier like you need to
start prep you know you're preparing for
for that way earlier. But they were like
that's the best best way to um to help
prevent I mean it's not like 100% gonna
stop you know stop dementia um but it's
giving you a much better uh chance to
not um develop dementia
>> right so 30 minutes for aerobic um
walking is you know that should be
lifelong you know like throughout your
life this is a great activity
>> the body is built on a system of use it
or lose it. So, the more you're able to
use it within reason, obviously within
the council of your healthcare provider,
um the better um in general. So, I hope
that answered your question, Renee.
>> Yes. All right. Rebecca is asking,
"Being a Seventh Day Adventist believer,
uh should you find a Seventh Day
Adventist therapist?" I'd like to answer
that first and then I'll let you go.
>> Who are you? Um, so I am a Seventh Day
Adventist therapist and I tell people
you absolutely I tell Adventists you
don't have to have a Seventh Day
Adventist therapist. Um, I know some
amazing Christian therapists that are
not Seventh Day Adventists and I know
some amazing um, non-Christian
therapists. I'm It's just true. They're
very good at what they do and the things
they're saying are true. If you feel
more comfortable with a 7-day advenist
therapist, well then by all means, find
one. There we're out there,
but we're there's not enough of us. So,
everybody is not going to get a Seventh
Day Adventist therapist. There's a lot
of Christian therapists who are very
good. They don't, you know, believe
everything we believe doctrinally, but
that's not what therapy is all about.
Therapy is not about um the therapist
um putting their belief system onto the
client. That's not the ethical thing to
do. Um we're here to help you with your
um your goals and to meet your goals. So
that's my answer. What's your answer,
Dr. White?
>> Um I would you know I would So you
nailed it. um in terms of like you you
want to make sure the person is skilled
to handle what you're dealing with. So
for example, if you came to me and
you're like, "Hey, let's let's deal with
trauma." I might be like, "Hey man, my
sister Tante, she she might have more
skills in that area as far as like you
you enjoy EMDR and this kind of stuff."
>> I do enjoy that. I'm not EMDR certified
though, but
>> but yeah, I mean like so there are some
there's some areas like Yeah, she might
she might help you more um with that. So
um so yeah so you need to understand
what is my issue and who has the skills
to deal with it. All right now that said
this is the question I was going to ask
you. What would be the advantage of a
person who's spiritually congruent with
you from a therapist? What's the
advantage?
um just they'll have a it's okay
speaking especially specifically of the
Seventh Day Adventist culture and faith
like having someone that understands
the culture um of Seventh Day Adventism
and kind of the belief system could be
helpful
um in certain situations.
Um
yeah, I don't know. I guess I mean
that's my answer to that. I just think
it could be helpful understanding the
culture, but I really go out of my way
because I see some Seventh Day
Adventists, but it's like definitely the
um the least of group of people that I
see. I see people from every walk of
life. So, I have to really um try to
meet them where they are at, try to use
my understanding of what I do know of
either their situation. I mean, I see
people who um we're going way off of
this question, but just to meet your
question, Dr. White, I mean, I see
people from the LGBTQ community. Now I
don't understand like my personal belief
system is
is what it you know what the Bible says
about that. But when I'm meeting with
them I'm not putting that belief system
on them in therapy. I'm here to try to
address your needs and goals and what
you're going through and what has
brought you here into therapy. So I
guess I say I I work so hard in doing
that to meet people where they are that
um
when you say what can you how can you
benefit every therapist should do that.
So even if a therapist does not know
what Seventh Day Adventists believe,
when you present to them, it is their I
feel like it's the therapist's
responsibility to either educate
themselves some on that and just try to
meet that client where they where they
are at and what they are needing.
Hopefully that makes sense.
>> Absolutely.
>> It's really the therapist's
responsibility.
>> Well, absolutely. Because
what you're ultimately getting at is
like what helps you be empathic,
>> right?
>> What helps you be respectful of this
person's position or world view? Um, and
that really is the therapeutic skill.
Like, so you could come into me with a
world view that is not my own, but I'm
going to have to I'm going to like have
to call upon skill to to be able to
still help you navigate the
psychological struggles you might be
having. Um, but but I just thought it
would be interesting to also reflect on,
hey man, what what is cool when a person
has a similar worldview to you? they
then yeah they they might have an easier
time maybe amassing more empathy. Who
knows?
>> This is an interesting question and this
is from we calling them uber cal 21 so I
don't know but um from it says is it
healthy for a person to take
extracurricular activities ex i.e
exercise, joining a sports screw up,
etc. to avoid tough conversations even
though it helps them mentally.
Again, I want to answer this first. I'm
like [laughter]
just a second. So, it's never healthy to
avoid a tough conversation. All of those
things that you listed are healthy
things. Like any person should be doing
should be exercising. They don't have to
join a a support group um or a sports
group, excuse me, but it's healthy. any
of all those things are healthy things
but nothing is healthy to avoid a tough
conversation. We have to learn how to
have tough conversations in a healthy
way. Um, we need to learn how to listen,
um, and be empathetic and listening to
the person. And we need to learn how to
be able to share what we're going to
share in the right tone with the right
spirit um, and in the right healthy
space with the other person. So, there's
never
um, a
ne it's never healthy to avoid
a tough conversation. I mean, maybe it
needs to happen in a certain place.
Maybe it doesn't need to happen right at
that moment. Maybe in a few days, maybe
whatever you're, you know, you're
thinking or praying about when's the
best time to do it, but never to avoid
it alto together for a long period of
time.
>> Yeah. So, you nailed it. Like just
because just because it's like you have
an urge to address something like like
I've said I've learned in my marriage
often time the first time I'm seeing it
it's not necessarily the moment like it
it's often it makes sense to think about
things for a little bit. Now, you do see
I I I did see this one coach who talked
about the fact that like, well, when
you're in like I this is the problem
with influencers. Sometimes they like
they're reductionistic and they're like
um yeah, when you're in therapy, you're
just talking about the negative. You're
just talking about the negative. And so,
it's almost like he was kind of um
casting shade on therapy and saying
avoid therapy and just have a good time
with the person.
>> Um no. Uh, like I think that's
reductionistic. Can we sometimes fight
too much? Sure.
>> Sure, you might fight too much. Um, can
we sometimes forget to have some fun
together? Sure. Sure. Sometimes we do
need to put more fun into the thing. But
to Sister Tante's point, should a
strategy be to avoid tough
conversations?
Um, [gasps and snorts]
no. That doesn't seem like a winning
strategy. Did Dr. Gotman talk about the
fact that there are conversations that
will never be resolved. And just know
that in the back of your mind, sure, but
that still doesn't mean you don't
develop the skills to argue fairly, to
argue respectfully, to argue in a way
that bars those four horsemen of the
apocalypse that he talks about that will
be a predictor for the relationship not
working out. Um, so but but you want to
develop the skills of being that safe
space that we were talking about,
>> right?
>> You know, where we can talk, we can
defer, but we can be respectful and
loving of each other. Um, so I would
agree that I don't see a really good I
don't see that as necessarily a good
strategic approach for long-term
intentional avoidance of necessary
conversations. Mhm.
Yes.
All right.
Well, guys, we are at the end of our
time together, but we are going to
continue our topic because I think it's
such a huge topic and we still uh we've
done two hours now, but that's still
just barely uh scratching the surface.
We want to go deeper. So please, like
you see on your screen there, it says,
"Please share this broadcast with your
loved ones, with your um the men in your
life." And again, women, you are
definitely welcome here because we uh
want to learn about how we can become um
and support the men in our lives better,
um their mental health, all of those
things. So your sons, your your
husbands, your brothers, your fathers,
friends, the men in your life, we want
to become a better support and we want
to um continue to take go and take a
deeper dive and and what how to help um
men and their mental health and women.
Don't think we've forgotten about you.
We will do a series for us too because
we know we go through a lot. But I'm
just happy to do this series with you,
Dr. white because we stated this at the
beginning, but men do they I don't know
because they don't speak up and out for
themselves. They don't advocate for
themselves all the time. They tend to
get forgotten and we just think like,
"Oh, they're quiet. They're fine." No,
no, no, no, no, no. Just because
somebody's not saying something does not
mean they're just fine.
>> That silence can mean a lot.
>> Powerful.
>> Um, so yes, let's try to show up for the
men in our lives. So, we will be back
here next week and we'll still be
talking about this same topic. So,
please bring your questions, share this,
invite someone to um our live broadcast
next week at this same time.
>> We look forward to seeing you there.
>> One one I have a funny feeling what the
next series will be, you know, since
we've been so gracious in addressing the
men. I I don't know. I think we I owe I
think the we owe women that as well.
>> Oh yes.
>> You know, wouldn't that be cool?
>> We're not going to leave the women out.
>> And for and for you guys, I just want to
leave you with the um it's a myth that
drowning occurs loudly. Actually,
drowning drowning victims are very
quiet. They're very quiet.
>> Um so so we want to be aware of that as
we're looking for people who might be
struggling. The first sign might be the
silence.
>> Absolutely. That was great. Thank you
for that. All right, guys. Have a good
evening and we will see you next week.
>> All right. Take care. Till next time.
>> All right. Bye bye.